# XIAOJIAN XU

# [Homepage] [Google Scholar] [Github] [Twitter] [Linkedin]

Department of Computer Science and Engineering 

Washington University in St. Louis

# About me

#### Current research

My current research pursues to combine computational imaging, optimization, and machine learning to enable new intelligent imaging technology for various imaging applications including denoising, deblurring, superresolution, image segmentation, optical microscopy, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), radar, and autonomous driving, etc. My research efforts are taking place at two complementary levels: (a) the fundamental and mathematical aspects of imaging; (b) application-oriented projects in collaboration with researchers in medicine, biology, and computer vision.

#### Research interests

Computational Imaging, Optimization, Deep Learning, Inverse Problems, Computer Vision, Signal Processing

# EDUCATION

# Washington University in St. Louis (WUSTL), St. Louis, MO, USA

9/2017-7/2022

• Ph.D student in Computer Science (GPA: 3.87/4.00), advised by Dr. Ulugbek Kamilov

University of Electronic Science and Technology of China (UESTC), Chengdu, China

9/2014-6/2017

M.Eng in Communication & Information Engineering (Graduated with Honors)

University of Electronic Science and Technology of China (UESTC), Chengdu, China

9/2010-6/2014

B.Eng in Communication Engineering (GPA: 3.89/4.00)

# WORK EXPERIENCE

### University of Michigan-Department of EECS

8/2022-present

Postdoctoral research fellow with Prof. Jeffrey Fessler

Ann Arbor

 Investigation of the development, implementation, and evaluation of image reconstruction methods based on data-driven approaches, especially as applied to applications with limited measurements and/or training data.

#### Facebook Reality Labs Research (FRLR)

5/2021-8/2021

Research intern with Dr. Brian Wheelwright

Seattle (remote)

 Built the ray-tracing model for peripheral display system in Oculus, solved its display calibration problem, and designed an efficient camera-to-display mapping for its real-time rendering using neural representation.

#### Mitsubishi Electric Research Laboratories (MERL)

5/2019-8/2019

Research intern with Dr. Hassan Mansour

Boston

 Investigated in 3D tomographic imaging problems and solved the problem by proposing two distinct methods, model-based optimization and data-driven deep learning.

# AWARDS & HONORS

#### Honors

| • | Honored Ph.D student in Computer Science & Engineering department | 2021 |
|---|---|------|
| • | Outstanding Graduate Student                                      | 2017 |

# Scholarship

| • | Graduate Student First-Rank Academic Scholarship  | 2016 |
|---|---|------|
| • | Graduate Student Second-Rank Academic Scholarship | 2015 |
| • | Graduate Student First-Rank Academic Scholarship  | 2014 |

National Inspirational Scholarship 2013

| People's First-Rank Scholarship   | 2012 |  |  |
|---|------|--|--|
| National Inspirational Scholarship  | 2011 |  |  |
| Others  |      |  |  |
| • Third-prize of 'Internet+' Entrepreneurship Competition in Sichuan Province | 2016 |  |  |
| <ul> <li>Great Award of Intelligent City Technology Competition</li> </ul>    | 2016 |  |  |
| <ul> <li>Award of Hackathon Programming Competition</li> </ul>                | 2015 |  |  |
| <ul> <li>Second Prize of Electronic Design Competition in UESTC</li> </ul>    | 2011 |  |  |
| Skills  |      |  |  |

- Languages: Python, Matlab, C, Java
- Skills: Optimization, Inverse problems, Tensorflow, Pytorch, Deep learning, Linux, TCP/IP

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

### Model-based deep learning for imaging and vision

8/2020 - Present

 Developed imaging-model-assisted learning methods such as unsupervised learning, self-supervised and deep unrolling framework for different imaging tasks with various noise corruption challenges ([1][2][3][5][9][10][12]).

### Learning-based optimization for imaging and vision

8/2020 - Present

• Extensively investigated in variants of Plug-and-Play priors (PnP) and Regularized by denoising (RED) approaches for various imaging tasks by combining the imaging models with the deep-learning priors, in both theory and practice ([2][3][6][7][8]).

# Compressed and stochastic algorithms for large-scale imaging

7/2018 - Present

 Investigated in large-scale imaging problems by developing stochastic variants of optimization- and learningbased algorithms with convergence guarantee ([1][9][10][13]).

### Some earlier research experience

3/2014 - 6/2017

- · Intelligent home system design and development.
- Routing and resource scheduling algorithms for large-scale software defined networks (SDN).

# **PUBLICATIONS**

#### **Preprints**

(\* indicates equal contribution)

- [1] J. Liu\*, X. Xu\*, W. Gan, S. Shoushtari, and U. S. Kamilov, "Online Deep Equilibrium Learning for Regularization by Denoising." arXiv, May 25, 2022. Accessed: Jul. 12, 2022. Available: http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.13051 [Paper]
- [2] Y. Hu, J. Liu, X. Xu, and U. S.Kamilov, "Monotonically Convergent Regularization by Denoising." arXiv preprint arXiv:2202.04961 (2022, accepted to ICIP). [Paper]
- [3] X. Xu\*, A. H. Al-Shabili\*, I. Selesnick, and U. S. Kamilov, "Bregman Plug-and-Play Priors." arXiv, Feb. 04, 2022. doi: 10.48550/arXiv.2202.02388 (2022, accepted to ICIP).[Paper]
- [4] S. Kahali, S. V. V. N. Kothapalli, X. Xu, U. S. Kamilov, and D. A. Yablonskiy, "Deep-Learning-Based Accelerated and Noise-Suppressed Estimation (DANSE) of quantitative Gradient Recalled Echo (qGRE) MRI metrics associated with Human Brain Neuronal Structure and Hemodynamic Properties," bioRxiv, 2021, doi: 10.1101/2021.09.10.459810. [Paper]

# **Published**

(\* indicates equal contribution)

- [5] X. Xu, S. V. V. N. Kothapalli, S. Kahali and U. S. Kamilov, and D. A. Yablonskiy, "Learning-based motion artifact removal networks for quantitative R2\* mapping," Magnetic Resonance in Medicine, vol. 88, no. 1, pp. 106–119, 2022, doi: 10.1002/mrm.29188. [Paper]
- [6] X. Xu, Y. Sun, J. Liu, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Provable Convergence of Plug-and-Play Priors with MMSE Denoisers," IEEE Signal Process. Lett., vol. 27, pp. 1280–1284, 2020. [Paper]
- [7] X. Xu, J. Liu, Y. Sun, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Boosting the Performance of Plug-and-Play Priors via Denoiser Scaling," in 54th Asilomar Conf. on Signals, Systems, and Computers, 2020, pp. 1305–1312. [Paper]

- [8] X. Xu\*, Y. Sun\*, Z. Wu\*, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Scalable Plug-and-Play ADMM With Convergence Guarantees," IEEE Trans. on Comp. Imag., vol. 7, pp. 849–863, 2021. [Paper]
- [9] J. Liu, Y. Sun, W. Gan, X. Xu, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "SGD-Net: Efficient Model-Based Deep Learning with Theoretical Guarantees," IEEE Trans. on Comp. Imag., vol. 7, pp. 598–610, 2021. [Paper]
- [10] J. Liu, Y. Sun, W. Gan, X. Xu, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Stochastic Deep Unfolding for Imaging Inverse Problems," in IEEE Int. Conf. Acoustics, speech and signal process (ICASSP), 2021, pp. 1395–1399. Paper
- [11] X. Xu, O. Dhifallah, H. Mansour, P. T. Boufounos, and P. V. Orlik, "Robust 3D Tomographic Imaging of the Ionospheric Electron Density," in 2020 IEEE Int. Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS), 2020, pp. 437-440. [Paper]
- [12] J. Liu, Y. Sun, X. Xu, and U. S. Kamilov, "Image Restoration Using Total Variation Regularized Deep Image Prior," in 2019 IEEE Int. Conf. Acoustics, speech and signal process (ICASSP), 2019, pp. 7715–7719. [Paper]
- [13] X. Xu and U. S. Kamilov, "SignProx: One-bit Proximal Algorithm for Nonconvex Stochastic Optimization," in IEEE Int. Conf. Acoustics, speech and signal process (ICASSP), Brighton, UK, May 2019, pp. 7800–7804. Paper

#### Invited talks

UCLouvain, Image and Signal Processing Group Seminar, 9/2020

# Professional Service

- Conference reviewer: ISBI, ICASSP
- Journal reviewer: IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP), IEEE Transactions on Computational Imaging (TCI), IEEE Transactions on Medical Imaging (TMI), Optics Communications, Scientific Reports, Signal Processing

# Teaching & Supervision Experience

# (Head) TA for Optimization

2019-2020

Assistant Instructor

St. Louis

· Served as the head assistant instructor and guest lecturer for course "Optimization" and "Large-Scale Optimization for Data Science" and obtained high evaluation from students.

Students supervision 7/2018-Present St. Louis

Research Supervisor

- Eddie Chandler, "Inhomogeneity correction for MRI", now B.S. student at WUSTL
- Yixuan Luo, "Deep-learning-based image segmentation", now M.S. student at WUSTL
- Michael Kincheloe, "Reinforcement learning for MRI artifacts correction". now B.S. student at WUSTL
- Zhixin Sun, "Neural representation for image reconstruction", coming Ph.D student at WUSTL
- Weijie Gan, "Fast MRI reconstruction and artifacts correction", now Ph.D student at WUSTL
- Jiarui Xing, "Deep-learning-based image artifacts correction", now Ph.D student at University of Virginia
- Shiqi Xu, "Sparse Fourier ptychographic microscopy", now Ph.D student at Duke University
- Hao Tang, "Adversarially robust classifiers for image reconstruction", now M.S. student at WUSTL
- Ryogo Suzuki, "Unfolding networks for image restoration", now at Rakuten Group, Inc.
- Yukun Li, "Single image denoising", now at Baidu Inc.
- Fa Long, "Dictionary learning for image restoration", now at Tencent Inc.